and what do people say about this?
а что у вас там люди про это
Well, they also swear because
говорят Ну тоже ругаются потому что у
many men have families with children. But
многих мужчин получаются семьи дети Но
they are taken away even if they have many children and they
их забирают даже если многодетные а
swear. Well, like here in America,
ругаются Ну как то вот у нас в Америке
if they swear, they go to rallies and
если бы ругаются это выходят на митинги
immediately make a demonstration of what is against
сразу делают демонстрацию что там против
there  like this And how they swear they go
там такого А у вас как ругаются они идут
to the head to the president Who is there they go to him
к главе к президенту Кто там вот к нему
and the president of Buryatia yes yes And what and
идут и президент у Бурятии да да И что а
he what Well, nothing he will do has already
он что Ну ничего что он сделает уже
been taken away yes he says I’ll give the money
забрали да говорит деньги
hello let’s talk normally
дам здравствуйте давайте нормально
Hello I’m originally from Rostov  But I’ve
Здравствуйте Я сам родом из Ростова Но
been living in California for 18 years And you’re from
живу в Калифорнии 18 лет А вы откуда
Buryatia And I have there What flag is lit
Бурятия А у меня там Какой флаг светится
you told me that Ukraine is lit
вы мне говорили что Украина светится
Ukraine And all because I installed VPN,
Украина А всё потому что я ставил VPN
talked to Ukraine for 2 hours and now I can’t
разговаривал с Украиной 2 часа и не могу
change it back,
никак теперь назад поменять у меня там
this flag is lit there and  you are from Buryatia
светится этот флажок а вы из Бурятии
where Ulan ud is from Yes yes my father
откуда Улан уд Да да у у меня отец
served in Ulan ud there in a military
служил в улану уд там в воинской
unit it’s cool So you see What a
части прикольно Так что видите Какой мир
round world the real world is of me My name is
круглый реально мир меня Меня зовут
Andrey And you are like Daria sirma Daria Irma
Андрей А вас как Дарья сырма Дарья Ирма
Daria - It’s in Buryat that this is a Russian
Дарья - Это по-бурятски что это русское
name  and Arma is what does a golden
имя а Арма это что означает золотая
woman mean? a golden woman is cool life and
женщина золотая женщина прикольно жи а
daria - it’s silver then yes
даря - это серебряная тогда да
Yeah And what And what do you communicate here
Ага А чем А чем тут общаетесь
and what do you communicate here, well, usually a
а а чем общаетесь тут ну обычно
casual conversation. I understand, you’re so
непринуждённый разговор Поня вы такие
cool, cheerful here, usually
прикольные весёлые тут обычно какие-то
everyone is drunk and angry. Your heart goes out to you.  just
все пьяные злые Вам Вам сердечко просто
Well done oh and it’s so calm there
Молодцы о а у вас там как спокойно
because my father is in Rostov, he
потому что вот у меня отец в Ростове то
says there they had drones flying
говорит там у них беспилотники прилетали
in Buryatia, it’s calmer yes Yes, it seems like
в Бурятии то спокойнее да Да вроде
there’s nothing yet Well, thank God Yes, that’s all
ничего нету пока Ну то слава Богу Да всё
that happens, your guys
а что получается ребят ваших где-то
were taken somewhere  war Yes, my classmate
забирали на войну Да у меня Одноклассник
was sitting at the same
сидели за одной
desk. Well, I’m like, I’ve already moved for 18 years and
партой Ну я я типа 18 лет уже как
from Russia, the only way I communicated with him was
переехал да из России то с ним общался
through the Internet, and they
только так через интернет и его вот это
took him away in the fall of twenty-two when
забрали когда была
he was mobilized in Ukraine somewhere in
мобилизация ему в Украине где-то в
Kherson region A drone flew right into the
Херсонской области Дрон прямо в лицо
face of a Russian via these
прилетел прямо в лицо ещё по эти по
Telegram
Telegram каналам
video channels A drone flew right into the face
видео русскому прилетел Дрон в лицо
like this, in short, it’s sad Do you have
такой короче печально У вас есть
any friends who have already died
какие-то знакомые которые погибли уже
too?
тоже Да друг дядя дядя на мине
And his friend, he saved his own and died, they
А друг он спасал своих и умер его тело
can’t find his body. And how his uncle and friend got
найти не могут А как дядя и друг попали
there for the
туда на
war as a volunteer, he went like this, and
войну добровольцем пошёл вот такой вот а
his uncle was taken away by mobilization, and he What
дядя его забрали мобилизация а он Кем
was he like in
был типа в по
life? In what sense? Well, like a student there, a
жизни В каком смысле Ну типа студент там
worker in a store, worked  who Well, an
рабочий в магазине работал кем А ну
ordinary blue-collar worker, an employee, yes, they took him away. It’s
обычный рабочий работник работник да е
just that I know so many stories.
забрали Просто я столько знаю историй Да
Yes, what can I do too, uh? Well, how is this
что у меня получается тоже ээ Ну как это
not my uncle? This is considered a cousin
не мой дядя Это двоюродный дядя
Yes, too, like they took him away and
считается Да тоже типа его забрали и
in short, they don’t know until now, like they don’t know,
короче не знают до сих пор типа не знают
died, disappeared  so-and-so By the way, I
погиб пропал безвести такой-то Кстати я
watched this It’s true that from
смотрел Вот это Это правда что из
Buryatia and Dagestan most of the
Бурятии и из Дагестана самое больше
dead Yes Buryatia Yes, a lot of it
погибших Да Бурятии Да очень много
just turns out that way I also can’t
так-то просто получается Я тоже не могу
understand why this is Moscow St. Petersburg they’re
понять почему вот это Москва Питер они
having fun Yes and the guys from the regions
себе гуляют Да а ребят из регионов
especially Dagestan  Buryatia There are so
особенно там Дагестан Бурятия Там и так
few people left and they take them.
мало осталось людей их берут
Well, what do you people say about it?
Ну а что у вас там люди про это говорят
Well, they also swear because many
Ну тоже ругаются потому что у многих
men have families with children. But they
мужчин получаются семьи дети Но их
take them even if they have many children, and they
забирают даже если многодетные а
swear like we do in America, if they
ругаются как вот у нас в Америке если бы
swear, they come out  rally and immediately
ругаются это выходят на митинг и сразу
make a demonstration, what is there against
делают демонстрацию что там против там
this? And how they quarrel with you, they go to the
такого А у вас как ругаются они идут к
head of the president Who is there, they go to him
главе к президенту Кто там вот к нему
and the president of Uti yes yes and
идут и президент Ути да да и
an Everything that he does has already been taken away yes he
ан Всё что он сделает уже забрали да
says the money I will give
говорит деньги дам
all the person’s money for money exchanged
всё деньги человека на деньги обменяли
Yes
да
Uh-huh Yes And your uncle it turns out they at least
Угу Да А у вас дядя получается ему хоть
paid him the money or if they didn’t find him
выплатили деньги или если его не нашли
then they didn’t pay no they found his uncle but they
то не выплатили нет дядю нашли а друга
didn’t find a friend, I don’t know what they
не нашли друга я не знаю вот что там
did there and it turns out that if they didn’t
сделали и получается из друга раз не
find a friend then they didn’t pay his mother for him and his
нашли то за него и не выплатили маме
wife  Yes, honestly, I don’t know this, I
жене Да вот честно я не знаю этого я
know that they didn’t find him, that
знаю то что вот то что его не нашли то
is, his friends said there, but they found his uncle,
есть друзья там сказали а вот дядю его
that is, he Well, everything is in
нашли то есть он Ну всё у него типа на
place, all the parts of his body were just
месте все части там тела просто вот
blown up and his uncle died, it’s his uncle  or
подорвался и Умер дядя это его дядя или
your uncle My uncle mo and how much
ваш дядя Мой дядя мо а и сколько за него
did they pay for it, how many millions are there, either
выплатили сколько там миллионов то ли
two or three fir-trees-sticks, so this is damn
два то ли три ёлки-палки так это блин
little. What is this? In our American way,
мало Это что Это по наше американский
it turns out to be how much 20,000 dollars
это получается сколько 20.000 долларов
or what? Well, apparently so
или что Ну видимо так
Damn, what about these 2  milna you can
Блин а что на эти 2 милна можно
buy a person’s life you can’t buy it no Well that’s
купить жизнь человека не купишь не Ну
right Well they paid it to the wife or
правильно Ну вот выплатили это жене или
whoever it’s paying the money to the
кому кому это вообще деньги выплачивает
wife Yes to the wife And what is she doing with them
жене Да жене И что она куда их
I forgot where she lives now the
она я забыла где она сейчас живёт
apartment I think my daughter bought that
квартиру по-моему дочке купила та какую
apartment for 2 million  this is 20,000 dollars,
квартиру за 2 млн это 20.000 долларов
I don’t know, maybe some small one-
это не знаю можно какую-то маленькую
room Khrushchev house can probably be
хрущёвку однокомнатную наверное можно
bought,
купить
I honestly don’t remember where they
вот я честно не помню где они сейчас
live now, but they
живут но они
moved as soon as they
переехали как только вот
took some
забрали какой-то
city. I mean, they left Ulan ud for a
город В смысле из Улан уд уехали в
small city, no, for a big
маленький город Да нет в большой
city.  I just don’t
город только не
remember Omsk Tomsk Omsk or Tomsk and she
помню Омск Томск Омск то ли Томск а она
was a Buryat or a Russian Buryat Well, the
бурятка или руская была бурятка А ну
Buryat and the EU is your
бурятка да ЕС это ваш
uncle the storm
дядя буря
left. Honestly, I don’t know either Why
уехали Вот честно не знаю тоже Почему
they left, I was interested in searching, I see
они уехали поис интересовал я смотрю у
here in California, I
нас тут в Калифорнии у меня в
studied at the university I I  a teacher at
университете училась я Я преподаватель в
the university and a girl from Buryatia studied with us. Well,
университете и у нас девушка из Бурятии
she also has a Russian name
училась Ну у неё русское тоже имя
for some reason, here’s her Russian name,
почему-то вот русское имя
uh, Oksana, she was and she, I’m with her
ээ Оксана она была и она вот я с ней
too, because I’m always interested
тоже потому что мне интересно всегда
when I see fellow countrymen from Russia. Yes, I
когда я земляков из России вижу Да я
ask how everything is there  and she says that
спрашиваю как там всё и она говорит что
Buryatia is a huge richer region, there is a
Бурятия огромный богатей регион там есть
forest, in short, there are minerals Yes,
лес короче есть полезные ископаемые Да
but people live very poorly. That is, it
но живут люди очень бедно То есть
turns out that everything is taken to Moscow by all the
получается что всё в Москву забирают все
resources, she says and people are forced to
ресурсы говорит и люди вынуждены бедно
live in poverty, yes Well, yes there is such a thing, how much is your
жить да Ну да есть такое сколько у вас
average salary there in Buryatia?  25 average 25 25,250
буряти средняя 25 средняя 25 25250
dollars apparently yes, but what can you
долларов видимо так да а что можно на
buy for 25,000 rubles per month? Well,
25.000 руб купить в месяц Ну
in general there are payments, but now they said
вообще есть выплаты но сейчас сказали
payments. Either they will give it in
выплаты Давать или не будут
January or in February they
получается января то ли с февраля
will start for non-working parents, that is,
начнут неработающим родителям то есть
in general, in
вообще в
principle, they will not give payments for
принципе не будут выплаты давать на
children and  from some Well, in general, I
детей и с какого-то Ну в общем выплаты
stopped giving payments because Well, since it
перестал давать так как Ну так как
used to be tough and you have children no,
раньше жесть а у вас дети есть нет
these are unmarried yes
эти незамужние да
yes, but how do the Russians treat you there
да а как к вам там русские относятся
because once upon a time the
потому что вот когда-то вот э ж Золотая
Mongolian Golden Horde Yes, it’s the other way around
Орда монгольская Да она ж наоборот
controlled all of Russia and the future, and
контролировала всю Россию да будущую и э
uh, these Russian princes, they went to
вот эти русские князи они ездили на
bow to Genghis Khan, yes And now the Russians,
поклон чингисхану да А сейчас русские
I’m Russian myself, yes, but I
вот мне я сам русский да но я историю
studied history normally, yes, but many of my
изучал нормально да А вот многие мои
peers, you know, they became some
сверстники Они знаете стали какими-то
kind of racist Nazis,
такими расиста нацистами
they start talking  that these
Они они начинают говорить что вот эти
all sorts of people are drilling the Caucasus and they were all running around
там всякие Кавказ бурят и всё они бегали
barefoot And we came They were given Civilization This is
босы А мы пришли Им дали Цивилизацию Вот
how I say how they gave Civilization if
так я говорю как дали Цивилизацию если
we were Russians Yes, the Mongols brought it when
нам русским Да монголы принесли когда
the device Yes Moscow
устройство Да Москву при монголах
was created under the Mongols, in
создали по
fact they
сути нормально
upset it normally Well here Yes, that’s how Irkutsk
расстроили Ну тут Да так-то Иркутск же
it turns out that it’s close to you and when
получается с ти рядом и Когда в Иркутск
you come to Irkutsk they just may not
приезжаешь просто могут квартиры не
rent out apartments. Well, even in Irkutsk. I know
сдавать Ну там ну даже в Иркут Я я знаю
that we have something like this in Rostov, and
что Вот такое у нас вот в Ростове есть
what do they write, for example, only to the Slavs?
да что э пишут например только славянам
Well, that was wild, although we have
Да вот и это было дико хотя у нас тут
very  there are many nationalities from the Caucasus and
очень много национальностей из Кавказа и
so on, but Irkutsk seems to be right
так всё да а Иркутск это же вроде прямо
next to Buryatia. These were your ancestral
рядом с бурятией Это ваши исконные
Buryat territories, and
бурятские территории же были и они вот
even Irkutsk residents say this when they come
говорят даже иркутяне Когда приезжают
to Buryatia, you know, maybe there is such a
вот в бурятию знаете может есть такой
village of
посёлок
Arshan where there is a datsan and where the mountains are
Аршан там где дацан есть да где горы там
peak of love They even come there,
пик любви Вот они даже туда приезжают
Irkutsk residents, and they can just talk to
иркутяне и просто могут вот так вот в
your face like that, you Buryats are nobody at all.
лицо тебе чить вы буряты вообще никто
Well, that is, they came to your
Ну да то есть они приехали на вашу
native land on which you lived from
родную землю на которой вы жили испокон
time immemorial, and it
веков да
turns out that they are the descendants of the invaders
они получается потомки захватчиков
who once captured this land  Yes,
которые когда-то захватили эту землю Да
and they come, damn it, it’s just tough. Well,
и они приходят блин это просто жесть Ну
some when they said that, they said so,
некоторые когда так говорили они
to grab the children, then the five-year-old Buryats
отхватить детей то пятилетние буряты
piled on these little hands, yes, 20 20 children. They
наваливают этим ручкам да 20 20 детей
could just attack four or five of
Просто могли на четверых на пятерых
them just for this. Well, beat them up
напасть просто их за это Ну поколотить
a little
немного
handsome, I say this.
красавчик говорю так
Unfortunately, they allow you to behave like this
сожалению позволяют так вести с собой Да
Yes, they are offended,
вот их обижают вот
these people are silent, if they are not silent, it’s
эти люди молчат если не молчат вот у нас
like in America. Yes, we too once
как в Америке Да у нас тоже когда-то
had one there too, for example, people with a
был тоже было там например людей с
certain skin color were not allowed
определённым цветом кожи не пускали
transport in schools;
транспорт в школах нельзя было учиться
we chose a democratic state
демократическое государство мы выбрали
that everyone has the right to respect, but
что все имеют право на уважение у на
even the president would be dark-skinned,
даже президент бы О он был темнокожий да
that is, for Russia to say such a thing,
то есть для России чтобы такое скажем
imagine that the president there would be,
представить что президентом будет там
for example, a Buryat, but someone not
например бурят Да вот кто-то не такой
like Slavyanskoe ve would immediately say no
как Славянское ве сразу бы говорили не
why do we need all these things there And so on
зачем нам эти там всякие И так дальше
Yes, so that’s why it’s necessary Yes, if they
Да так что поэтому нужно Да если по
start to offend it on a national basis, it’s
национальному признаку начинают это
necessary to firmly put it in its place,
обижать надо жёстко ставить на место
always
всегда
here the beats gathered in beating handsome
вот такты собрались в лупили красавчики
fifteen-year-old boys because you need to
пацаны пятнадцатилетние потому что нужно
defend the honor there is such a thing Yes, here in
отстаивать есть такое Да вот у меня в
Rostov Yes  one of my Odnoklassniki,
Ростове Да у меня один из Одноклассников
he is also some kind of
он тоже какой-то
askin, in short, he was still a fool at school, he
аскин короче он что-то в школе ещё
smoked, he drank, and he became a university. He
дурачок был Курил пил а стал университет
went. Yes, he was kicked out after the first year
Пошёл Да его выгнали после первого курса
and he gave in to something like. Now,
и он подался както там типа Вот сейчас
like the Russian community, you also
как русская община есть у вас тоже там
have that there.  Russian community of
есть та русская община
Buryatia Yeah Probably they go there in
Бурятия Ага Наверное они там ходят
short like they are Slavs there
короче такие типа они там славяне
patrol Slavic Yes there
патруль Славянский Да там
to And by the way you study the Buryat language
чтобы А у Вас кстати язык бурятский
in schools
изучают в школах
yes that is but mathematics and physics everything is in
да то есть но математику физику всё на
Russian Yes all these subjects Yes well there are
русском Да все эти предметы Да ну есть
separate schools Well here is Ulan  maybe
школы отдельные Ну вот Улан где могут
just in Russian Well, in a lesson they
просто на русском языке Ну вот на уроке
can just ask you in Buryat, that
тебя просто бурятском могут спросить то
is, there Every child must know the
есть там Каждый ребнок должен знать
Buryat language, that is, in order to get into
бурятский язык то есть чтобы попасть в
this school You need to pass an exam in the
эту школу Тебе нужно пройти экзамен на
Buryat language Yeah, it’s interesting for the
бурятский язык Угу интересно на
Basics, I understand How are you? Well, you’re
Основы понял А как у вас Ну у вас
doing well  As I understand it from the census I
получается я так понимаю по переписи Я
looked at the Buryats are about 20 or 30% Yes in the
смотрел бурятов где-то 20 или 30% Да в
Republic Yes by the way Yes there is little storm
Республике Да кстати Да мало буря есть
under the Soviet Union and the
получается при Советском созе и
Russian Empire they were populated specifically by
Российской империи заселяли специально
Russians like to dilute
русскими типа чтобы разбавить
you Apparently yes
вас Видимо да
ru And now your guys are also being sent
ру А сейчас ещё ваших парней отправляют
to you and  there are so few left Yes,
на вас и так мало осталось Да в
your guys are sent to the republic to
республика ваших парней отправляют на
war So that there are even fewer and then
войну Чтобы ещё меньше было а потом
these from Omsk Irkutsk will come
будут приезжать вот эти с Омска Иркутска
and poke you that you are a small people
и тыкать вам что вы малочисленный народ
like Indians Yes
типа Как индейцы Да
yes there is such a thing I by
да есть такое Я
the way
кстати
lived another 10 years somewhere or back  there was a
пом ещ лет 10 где-то или во назад был
film I watched, I was already in America, yes, but I
фильм смотрел я уже в Америке был да Но
watched a film called To Baikal called Uh-huh,
смотрел фильм На Байкал называется Угу
some KVN team of yours filmed how They
ваша какая-то КВН команда сняла как Они
went to Baikal there, this is something from
ехали на Байкал там вот это что-то из
the street, in my opinion, something Irkutsk, too, something
ула по-моему чтото Иркутск тоже что-то
was like that here too  there
было такое вот тут тоже там какие-то
were some little notes there They had
немножко нотки были такие У них
Russian ones for 9 seconds, go about the hero
российские на 9 секунд сходите про героя
sailor Aldar
моряка алдара
Tsydenzhapov and what kind of hero is the sailor who
цыденжапова а что за герой маряк который
saved on the ship Yes
Спас на корабле Да
348 people o What kind of ship is this What kind of
348 людей о Это что за корабль Что за
war was it, well, in my opinion he just
война была ну это он просто по-моему
served and  so he saved his own Well, it’s like
служил и вот и спас своих Ну это типа
where it
где это
was in what year it’s not like this
было в каком году это ни как будто эта
war
война
but what year long ago 1900 some year
а какой год давно 1900 какой-то год
in Vladivostok he served Well, I understand
во Владивостоке он Служил А ну понял
In short, there may be some kind of Russian-Japanese
Короче какая-то русско-японская может
war there or something, but it turns out  this is
война там или что да а получается это
this, it’s like the local film studio shot
Это у вас типа местная киностудия сняла
it in Buryat yes yes but well, well,
именно Бурятская да да но ну как ну это
this film is in all
этот фильм есть во всех
cinemas And what is it called 9
кинотеатрах А как называется оно 9
seconds
секунд
like that And damn they
так А блин
switched someone asked what is the
переключились кто-то спрашивал что какая
faith of the Buryats,
вера у бурятов
Buddhists so like subscribe comment they
буддисты так лайк подписка комент хорошо
promoted the Buryats well  to the conversation but
раскрутили буряток на разговор но
was cut off subscribe to Telegram right
оборвалось подпишись на Telegram прямо
now the axis of wine and for now
зараз ось вин а
it is more and more important YouTube keeping
пок це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube заня
us busy through skarg or in your ban and even
нас через скарг ор в твый бан и дуже
more videos I don’t show people at the moment I don’t
багато вдео не показую людям вчасно не
show information about streams For this
показуе информация про стрими Тому для
purpose, we need Mali operational link
того щоб ми Мали оперативний зв'язок
write directly at the same time and while there in telegra
пишиться прямо зараз а пок там в телегра
okm video sche tezh tsikava and korisna
окм видео ще теж цикава и корисна
information and we will
информация и мы пон вами трима постийний
show you about it
незалежно в того чи покаже вам про це
YouTube Glory to Ukraine subscribe
YouTube Слава Украине подпишись